They stopped in the end. We are picking up in the middle
of דף מ"ח עמוד ב'. Daf Mem Chet Amud Bet. We're still
on a couple of digressions relating to, not digressions but anyway special
cases relating to all these issues about the wheat. So let's take
a look. We had just asked a fascinating question about what happens
when it rains wheat? But now we are in the dung. Right?
And the wheat in the dung and the kernels from the dung.
Now we are by רבי שמעון בן פזי. Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi.
It is seven lines before the lines get wide,
12 lines from the bottom of the page. בעא רבי שמעון בן
פזי, Ba'a Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi, Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi asked the
following question: שבולת שהביאה שליש קודם העומר ועקרה ושתלה לאחר העומר. Shibbolet
she-hevi'ah shlish kodem ha-Omer ve-akrah u-sh-talah le-achar ha-Omer. So you have a
שבולת, shibbolet, a stalk, that was a third ripe. Third ripe is
critical for the גמרא Gemara because a third ripe is when the
grain becomes fit for being חייב chayav in תרומות T'rumos and מעשרות.
Ma'asros.
Okay, so the same measure as cutting of meat, right?
The, oh that's interesting. That's the debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות,
Tosafot, right? Or not Rashi, הרמב"ם, ha-Rambam, whether מאכל בן דרוסאי Ma'achal
Ben Derusai is a third or a half. But okay, that's a
good point. But that's considered to be like a גמרא פרי. Gemara
p'ri. Okay, so what happened is you, it brought a third. Now
here we're still going to be in the תרומות T'rumos and מעשרות
Ma'asros level. ועקרה, Ve-akrah, you uprooted it and then ושתלה לאחר העומר,
ve-sh-talah le-achar ha-Omer, and then the עומר Omer came and then you
planted it. Now why is that relevant? Because when you uprooted it
and now, so halachically what you have now is considered grain, meaning
if it was before it came a third then this wouldn't be
grain, it would be fodder, it wouldn't even have a status of
grain. But now that it's a third ripe, meaning it's half-ripe, what
you have is considered grain. And now the עומר Omer comes. So
the עומר Omer now makes this permissible, but this is already picked
grain. Now after the עומר Omer you replanted it. Now you planted
the seed, you actually replanted the stalk. So you plucked the stalk,
halachically it was now grain, the עומר Omer came and now you
replanted the stalk. Now if that seed had continued to grow and
the עומר Omer came, then the continued growth of what was planted
when the עומר Omer came obviously was already made permissible by the
עומר. Omer. But that's not really what happened here. This is like
the עומר Omer came and I planted, if I planted new seeds
after the עומר, Omer, then what grew wouldn't be permissible, I would
need the next עומר. Omer. And this is like exactly inhabiting that
middle ground. It's not new seeds, right? Because if I didn't take
the seed out and plant it then it would be a new
planting. I planted the thing that had been planted before. So to
what degree is this a new planting or continuation of the old?
And does the עומר, Omer, is what grows now permissible or forbidden?
Okay, ועקרה, ve-akrah, so you uprooted it, ושתלה לאחר העומר, ve-sh-talah le-achar
ha-Omer, and you planted it after the עומר, Omer, והוסיפה, ve-hosifah, and
it continued to grow. Now the גמרא Gemara here is assuming that
it's taken for granted that it is considered a new planting and
the stuff that grows now new is actually not permissible. It's not
like it was continuously in the ground when the עומר Omer came.
So what grows new is now forbidden until the next עומר. Omer.
So now in this stalk of wheat, you have a percentage of
it which grew and the עומר Omer made permissible and a percentage
of it which
then was replanted and continued to grow and is now חדש. chadash.
So it's a mixture half and half. So how do you treat
this? Okay, so let's take a look.
מהו, mahu, what's the law? בתר עיקר אזלינן, Batar ikar azlinan, do
you go by the עיקר, ikar, the foundation? Meaning the base, the
base stalk was permissible already and therefore what grows afterwards should be
considered secondary to it and it should basically all be considered permissible.
ושריא עומר, Ve-shar'ya Omer, and the עומר Omer already made it permitted.
או דילמא בתר תוספת אזלינן, O dilma batar tosefet azlinan, or maybe
you go by the addition that grows afterwards, meaning you also pay,
the addition that grows has its own status, ועד שיבא עומר הבא,
ve-ad she-yavo Omer ha-ba, this is a mixture of permitted and forbidden
and you have to wait till the next עומר. Omer. So it's
clear that what grows afterwards it says is considered a new planting
and the עומר Omer has not related to it. But maybe it
is subservient to the base of the stalk itself, to what you
started with, the foundation, and therefore it's all permitted. Okay, so that's
the question. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תיפשוט ליה מהא
דאמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן, Tifshot lei me-ha de-amar Rabbi Abbahu
amar Rabbi Yochanan, let's infer it from what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. ילדה שסבכה בזקינה,
Yalda she-sivcha be-z'keina, a young one that was intertwined with an old
one. Now this is talking about the question about ערלה. Orlah. And
you have a tree that has yet to have grown three years,
so any fruit that grows from it is ערלה. Orlah. And you
have a tree that's been growing for a long time and the
fruit that grows from it is not ערלה. Orlah. Now what does
it mean intertwined? So the, literally the image that it conjures up
and תוספות Tosafot actually says that this is the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, is
that you have both things growing and their sort of branches are
intertwined. And the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that somehow if their branches get
intertwined before the young one takes root, then when the, if they
first were intertwined and then the young one takes root, that the
young one is really just considered an extension of the old one
and not a separate tree. That's the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi wants
it, but that does not seem to be the way our גמרא
Gemara learns it. Our גמרא Gemara seems to understand that intertwined really
here means grafted, although the גמרא Gemara has other ways of saying
grafted like הרכיב, hirkiv, but okay, it's understood it means grafted. So
I took a branch from a... from a young tree, a tree
that hasn't grown three years, and I grafted it onto an old
tree, and there was already some fruit growing from it, and now
it continued to grow. So the fruit that was growing from prior,
that's the way the גמרא Gemara understands this case, is already ערלה.
Orla. Now it's grafted onto the new tree, it continues, the old
tree, it continues to grow. Is the additional growth we're going to
assume is non-ערלה? Orla? Because it's ultimately now connected to the old
tree and it's now growing. So the additional growth is now היתר,
Heter, but it's adding to an original growth which was איסור. Issur.
So let's take a look. ילדה שסבכה בזקנה, Yaldah she-sibkhah bi-zekeinah,
so this young tree that was intertwined with an old one, which
we're saying means grafted, ובא פירות, u-bah perot, there were already fruit
on it when it was grafted on, אפילו הוסיף במאתים אסור, afilu
hosif be-matayim assur,
even if now the additional growth is 200 times the original, it's
forbidden. ערלה Orla is בטל batel in 200. So if you have
a little bit of ערלה Orla got mixed up, one apple of
ערלה Orla got mixed up with 200 apples of non-ערלה, Orla, it's
בטל. batel. Here it says however, even if it was a tiny
growth that began and you grafted it and now it's grown to
200 times the original size, it still is forbidden. Now why? Why
isn't it בטל? batel? So the reason it seems is because since
the עיקר, ikar, the foundation, you know, that you started with was
forbidden, even when you add afterwards, it remains forbidden. So there you
see you go by the עיקר ikar to be strict. So maybe
we're saying we should by analogy go by עיקר ikar to be
lenient? In our case we have you start with a foundation of
the wheat that was permissible after the עומר. Omer. More grew that
was forbidden, maybe the more that grew should be secondary to the
עיקר, ikar, to the foundation. Here you're strict, maybe we should say
the same thing to be lenient. Okay. ואפילו הוסיף במאתים אסור. ve-afilu
hosif be-matayim assur. ואמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Ve-amar
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, and Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
said in the name of Rabbi Yonatan a very similar ruling. בצל
ששתלו בכרם, Batsal she-shatalo be-kerem, an onion that you planted an onion
in a vineyard. Now that's a problem of כלאים, Kilayim, כלאי הכרם.
Kilei Ha-Kerem. So that before we were ערלה, Orla, now we're כלאים,
Kilayim, you planted your onion in a vineyard ונעקר הכרם, ve-ne-ekar ha-kerem,
and then you basically totally removed the vineyard, so you have your
onion continuing to grow. The first little growth it did was a
כלאים Kilayim growth. Now you've removed your vineyard, the onion is still
growing, the additional growth is a non-כלאים Kilayim growth. So then what
happens? Same הלכה. Halacha. אפילו הוסיף במאתים אסור, afilu hosif be-matayim assur,
even if it continued to grow now 200 times the original size
of that little planting of an onion, it remains forbidden. Even though
normally כלאים, Kilayim, like ערלה, Orla, is permissible if it's less than
one in 200. So why? You have 200 times the growth of
היתר Heter because that growth of היתר Heter was built off an
origin, off of a base of איסור. Issur. And since it was
built off of a base of איסור, Issur, it becomes like the
איסור Issur and it does not work to create ביטול. bittul. So
we want to say the same in reverse to be lenient. If
you replanted this stalk after the עומר Omer and it continues to
grow, although now the new stuff is forbidden, it's growing on a
base of a permissible grain and should be considered permissible. Okay, says
the גמרא, Gemara, so that should be your answer. So it says
no. היא גופא קמיבעיא ליה, Hee gufah ka miba'ya leh, that was
exactly his question, whether you could learn it from that case or
not. נפשט פשיטא להו לרבנן דבתר עיקר אזלינן, Nifshat peshitah lehu le-rabbanan
de-batar ikar azlinan, is it clear to the Rabbis that we go
after the foundation, the base? לא שנא לקולא ולא שנא לחומרא, lo
shenah le-kula ve-lo shenah le-chumra, it doesn't matter if you're being lenient
or being strict. So you gave me examples of being strict, but
we would also apply this principle to be lenient, it's a fundamental
principle you always go by the base. עוד דילמא ספוקי מספקא להו,
Od dilma sapukei maspika lehu, or maybe they have a doubt whether
you go by the base or not.
ולחומרא אמרינן, u-le-chumra amrinan, we say it to be strict in the
case before about ערלה Orla and כלאים, Kilayim, לקולא לא אמרינן, le-kula
lo amrinan, but we would not say it to be lenient. So
yes, we understand that there could be this idea that everything is
defined by the base, but maybe yes, maybe no, we'll be strict
about it and not lenient about it, תיקו. teiku. So we don't
have a good answer. So this is interesting because it is different
than normal laws of ביטול, bittul, you know, and it is a
very good question, you know, already, you know, it's almost like if
you weren't in the גמרא Gemara mindset, you would already intuitively understand
that this is a different case. Why is it? So you have
something that's forbidden and you plant it and it continues to grow.
Like who would think to say, okay, the new stuff is איסור
issur and the old stuff is היתר heter and it's a תערובת
ta'arovet and is this בטל? batel? You know, almost that's like, what?
Yeah, make up your mind.
Right, decide. Now that it's growing, is it basically the way it
started? Is it the way it's grown now? Do you go בתר
עיקר? batar ikar? Do you not go בתר עיקר? batar ikar? And
that was really what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, are we
going to sort of conceptually distinguish this as two types of things
mixed together and then just say you go by רוב rov or
whatever or ביטול, bittul, or are we going to say no, you
know, if it started one way, it's considered to be a continuation
of the way it started? Okay, so that the גמרא Gemara says
we don't know. Okay, now we're going to have a series of
questions that are variations on that theme.
בעי רבה לענין מעשר מה, Ba'ei Rabbah le-inyan ma'aser mah, what would
be a similar case when it came to not a question of
חדש chadash but a question of מעשר? ma'aser? היכי דמי, Heichi dami,
what's the case? כגון דאמדנהו, Ke-gon de-amdinehu, now we're at the top
of ע"א, ayin amud aleph, like we estimated it, meaning you harvested
your grain, you said okay, I have a hundred bushels here, דעשרינהו,
de-asreinu, you took מעשר, ma'aser, ושתלינהו, ve-shatlinehu, now so you took מעשר,
ma'aser, so now you have You take ten bushels you gave it
to the לוי Levi of ninety bushels now that are מותר. mutar.
And normally what would you do in a normal year? In a
normal year you have these ninety bushels you'd eat some of it
some you would keep the seeds of and replant for the following
year. But again here you're not replanting the seeds. If you're replanting
the seeds then obviously now it's like a new a new thing.
New seeds replanted now they become obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot
again once they get replanted. But instead of replanting the seed you
went ahead and you replanted the stalks. So again we got this
whole question. It's not a new thing it's a is it a
continuation of the old? דעשרינהו de'asrinehu you took מעשר maaser ושתלינהו veshatlenhu
and now you replanted the stalks that you already had taken תרומות
ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot from. ואוסיפו להו ve'osifu lehu and now more grew.
אם תימצי לומר im timtzi lomar לא אזלינן בתר עיקר. lo azlinan
batar ikar. Let's say we have resolved based on the past question
that we're not going to be lenient to go by the עיקר.
ikar. If we were lenient to go by the עיקר ikar then
we would say that what grew now new is not חייב chayav
in תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'maasrot. It's an adding on to a base
that is permissible and therefore it's okay. So but we're going to
assume you don't go by דעיקר de'ikar you pay attention to the
new stuff that grew and it has its own status. לא אזלינן
בתר עיקר lo azlinan batar ikar ותוספת בה איסורי vetosefet bah issurei
and now you have to take מעשר maaser off of the new
stuff that grew. So now we're going to ask the opposite extreme.
If you pay attention to the new stuff especially when you're being
strict maybe the new stuff should redefine the status of the old
stuff. And now if this new stuff grew let's say now doubled
in the original size or quantity do you take מעשר maaser off
of fifty percent of the total grain or a hundred percent? Does
the fact that now you pay attention to the new stuff redefine
even the base? Okay so maybe we're going to the opposite extreme.
עיקר מאי? ikar mai? So what about the base? So does that
now also become obligated? So there are three possibilities right? Everything goes
by the base everything goes by when it grew or you know
everything goes by if it were the stricter half whether the stricter
is the base or the new that redefines everything. Okay so אמר
ליה אביי. amar leh Abbaye. So אביי Abbaye back to רבא Rava
or רבה Rabbah question of the גירסא. girsa. אביי Abbaye back מאי
שנא מכל חיטי ושערי דעלמא? mai shna mikol chitei us'arei de'alma?
Why is this different than any wheat or barley of the world?
You replant the seeds and everything that grows new is now חייב
chayav in תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot fully. So there's an obvious answer.
אמר ליה amar leh back to him no. דבר שזרעו כלה לא
מיבעיא לי. davar shezaro kaleh lo mibaya li. Something that the seed
ultimately disintegrates I have no question. You take a seed you plant
it the seed disintegrates something new grows obviously what grows is a
totally new story and therefore the whole thing is חייב chayav in
תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'maasrot. כי
קמיבעיא לי ki kamibaya li my
question is דבר שאין זרעו כלה מאי? davar she'ein zaro kaleh mai?
This is not you plant a seed and the seed disintegrates. You're
replanting the stalks. The base is there in front of you. The
old base is still around when it comes time to harvest. And
now the question is do I take תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot off
of the old base? I already took תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'maasrot. Or
does the fact that it continued to grow redefine it as completely
something new? Okay so it's clearly like three possibilities. One is the
new stuff that grows is seen as a part of the old
and doesn't require תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot or no חדש chadash or
nothing you know when you're replanting something. The other possibility is each
thing is separate. The new stuff is חייב chayav the old stuff
is not. And the third possibility is the new stuff if it's
more strict redefines even the old. Okay so that's his question. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי? mai? What's the story? תפשוט ליה מהא
דאמר רב יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן. tifshot leh me'ha de'amar Rav Yitzchak
amar Rabbi Yochanan. Why not let him infer it from the statement
of רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak in the name of רבי יוחנן? Rabbi
Yochanan? ליטרא בצל. litra batzal. You have a liter of onions שתיקנו
shetikno that you were fixed meaning you took תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot
from וזרעו vezaro and now you replanted the onions and in order
to grow
more ומתעשר לפי כולו. umit'aser lefi kulo. And now you harvest so
you took a liter of onions you planted them and they grew
more and now you harvested them after they grew. And now you
have to take תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot again because new stuff grew.
And it says מתעשר לפי כולו. mit'aser lefi kulo. You take מעשר
maaser from the total amount in front of you even though you
started with whatever the original amount was a liter's worth that had
already תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'maasrot. So you planted a liter of onions
you now harvest a few months later thirty liters of onions. You
take מעשר maaser off of thirty. But really only twenty-nine is new.
One was already there and already had תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot taken
from it. Is that the case clear? So the base
although you have to take מעשר maaser off of the base again.
That's exactly your question. Once more grows all is considered new and
you take מעשר maaser again off of the base. So he
says התם היינו זריעתו. hatam hainu zri'ato. No no that's different.
There that's exactly what how you sort of grow onions is you
plant now is that true? How do you what do you do
if you want to grow new onions? How do you do it?
Well that's right it's not seeds it's like bulbs right.
Grown bulbs and once you've planted an onion and it'll come up
again. They will come up again the next year.
But what do they they must leave something behind in the land
to come up again. What do they leave behind like little seedlings?
No no how do you get the bulbs in the first place?
You have to plant the bottom of a scallion.
So those bulbs are what is re so those are They grow
and
then they grow new bulbs.
No, no, they're from the roots.
Yeah, so
if you go to the store and you buy bulbs, yeah, they,
those grew somewhere and were taken out.
Right, so that's what it's understanding. It is understanding next, right, right.
Okay, I don't know about the next. Anyway, it's understanding that this
case, it's understanding, okay, it's understanding that this case, if
you go to the store and you buy the bulb,
well let me think, where does it grow? From the ground? Right.
Let's not worry about next year. This is understanding that a way
of growing onions, a way of growing onions, I don't know if
it's the only way, a way of growing onions is you take
the bulbs. So what it's saying is, my point is, well that's
the natural way in which you grow it, it's like planting seeds.
When you plant seeds, if I plant a, if I take a
bushel of seeds and I plant, and then six months later I
harvest the wheat, I take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros over everything, not
everything minus a bushel. So here too, if I plant a bushel
of onion bulbs, I'm going to take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros over
everything. Now before, the גמרא Gemara said that it was true about
wheat because the wheat, the seed disintegrated, and the seed doesn't disintegrate
by the onion. So here the גמרא Gemara is essentially revising that
and saying, okay, forget disintegrating. It doesn't matter, but if this is
the natural way in which you plant the thing and it grows,
then we're going to look at everything that now you harvest as
new, even though a little percentage is old. But when you're replanting
a stalk, since that's unusual, then we might not look at everything
as new, we might look as the old as still there and
still old. So that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. Is the גמרא Gemara
says: התם היינו זריעתה. Hasam, haynu zriata.
There, that is the way you plant onions. So it's true the
seed does not disintegrate, but when you plant onions, you plant the
bulbs and you harvest, everything you harvest is new and you take
מעשר maaser off of everything. הכא לאו היינו זריעתה. Hacha, lav haynu
zriata. Here, that is not the normal way it's planted and therefore
maybe the base is still the base and is not redefined by
the new growth. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara does not have an
answer about that. Now we're saying the new growth definitely has its
own status. Does it redefine the base or not? That we're not
clear. Now we have a, more you can see that they're starting
to have fun because of the next case. Let's take a look.
אמר ליה רבי חנינא בר מניומי לאביי. Amar ley Rabbi Chanina bar
Minyumi le-Abaye. So רבי חנינא בר מניומי Rabbi Chanina bar Minyumi says
to אביי: Abaye: עציץ שאינו נקוב מהו? Atiz she-eino nakuv mahu? So
what's the story about an, about a flower pot without a hole?
The גמרא Gemara loves its עציץ נקוב, Atiz Nakuv, right? It has
a flower pot, the idea of a flower pot with a hole
in it. And the idea of a flower pot with a hole
in it, normally and then you put it on the ground, so
then it becomes considered like a little bump in the ground and
it's considered and it's חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Without
the hole in it, so it's not physically connected to the ground,
it's פטור patur in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros at least דאורייתא. de-Oraisa.
So he said, well what happens if you have stuff growing in
a flower pot without a hole? So he says, well what kind
of question is that? מהו? Mahu? So the גמרא Gemara says: אי
לאו נקוב הלא לאו נקוב. Ee lo nakuv, halo nakuv. If there's
no hole, there's no hole. What are you asking me this question
for? No, no, דילמא dilma maybe this is what your question was
about. חזר ונקבו קאמרת. Chazar ve-nakvo ka-amart. Maybe we're talking that it
started without a hole and then you made a hole in it.
So here's like a perfect example of the base is not obligated
and the new stuff is like the reverse is obligated, right? So
it started without a hole, a certain amount grew, not חייב chayav
in תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, you made a hole. Now everything that
grows afterwards is חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. So that's
by analogy, does it now redefine the stuff that had been growing
prior? Okay, so that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says: מיהת
הכא חדא זריעה היא איחבורי הוא דקא מיחבר. Me-at, hacha, chada zria
hu. Ichburei hu de-ka michaber. Here it's all one planting and it's
stuff now after you made the hole being connected to the ground.
So that's distinct, ועולה, ve-oleh, and it keeps and now it grows.
התם, Hasam, by your case about taking מעשר maaser and then replanting
the stalks, שתי זריעות נינהו. shtei zriot inhu. That was two separate
plantings, so maybe the הלכה halacha is different. Now different which way?
רש"י Rashi is not so clear. רש"י Rashi sounds like he's saying
that if it's one planting, it's more that we should look at
the old stuff as separate because you haven't somehow redefined it. It
was there and then new stuff naturally grew on itself. When you
replant it, maybe the action of replanting the stalk redefines the old
stuff as now something new and now part of a new planting.
You could say the opposite, the שיטה מקובצת Shitta Mekubetzes says. He
says when you had no hole and now you made a hole,
even the old stuff is now growing from the ground. So the
fact that the old stuff is now growing from the ground itself
should redefine the old stuff. Whereas in the other case, you had
taken תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, replanted, the old stuff still remains exempt.
So with either way you could go with saying this is a
similar case but maybe deserves separate consideration because it is not a
new planting, it's old and new but it's sort of a natural
continuation. Okay, moving on.
Growing things in water and certain places in Israel to avoid all
this.
Yes, yes, hydroponics. And that's by שמיטה Shmita connected to the ground.
Right,
exactly, exactly. Yep, okay. בעי רבי אבהו. Ba-i Rabbi Abahu. Now רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abahu asked.
שבולת שמרחה בכרי. Shibbolet she-marcha ba-keri. You have your, your stalks that
you smoothed in the pile. smoothed over on the pile of grain
and that's the moment when they're חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות Terumot
u'Ma'asrot is when you smooth them over, ושתלה, u'shatalah, and then it
was so. There it was חייב chayav as opposed to before. Before
we were talking that you took your מעשר Ma'aser and then you
replanted it, so you started with a base that was exempt. Here
we're saying the opposite: it was חייב chayav in מעשר Ma'aser and
fully raised, got to the level of חיוב, chiyuv, it would have
been טבל Tevel to eat from it, you would have transgressed טבל
Tevel to eat from it, and now you replanted it. Okay, so
what's going to be the question? פקע ליה שמו במחובר. Paka lei
shemo be-muchar. Now it's growing and you're now saying that's תרומה. Terumah.
Okay, normally you could never say for growing stalk grain that's תרומה.
Terumah. Something can only become תרומה Terumah after it's cut and harvested
and processed and made into the pile. But all of that happened
to this grain. So when it was in the pile you could
have called it תרומה, Terumah, and it was at a state where
it was טבל Tevel and could be תרומה, Terumah, and now it's
replanted. So maybe the fact that you replanted should not take it
out of its previous status and it should have the potential and
ability to be, have the designation of תרומה. Terumah. So this isn't
the question of the new growth, this is the question of does
the replanting completely redefine it as
מחובר mechubar or does it still have the old status and it
could still become תרומה? Terumah? Okay, מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha?
כיון דמרחיה טבליה, Keivan de-marchei tivleh, since you smoothed it on the
pile, you made it into טבל. Tevel. טבליה לה, Tivleh lah,
and the fact that it's טבל Tevel on the one hand means
it's forbidden to be eaten, but on the other hand means it
has the potential of becoming תרומה, Terumah, right? It's sort of all
you need now to designate the תרומה, Terumah, that happens automatically. So
כי קרא ליה שם קדשה לה, Ki karei lei shem kadshah lah,
so when you designate it, you sanctify it even though now it's
growing. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say כיון דשתלה פקע
ליה טבליה, Keivan de-shatlah paka lei tivleh, once you replanted it, it
no longer is considered טבל. Tevel. It was טבל, Tevel, but now
it's considered part of the ground and a growing plant, and a
growing plant isn't טבל, Tevel, and if it's not טבל, Tevel, it
can't become תרומה. Terumah. פקע טבליה מיניה, Paka tivleh minei, the טבל
Tevel disappears from it. So אמרו ליה רבנן לאביי, Amru lei Rabbanan
le-Abaye, the rabbi said to Abaye, ואי אמרת הכי, Ve-i amrat hachi,
if that's true, you're thinking that you can call something תרומה Terumah
even now that it's growing? אם כן מצינו תרומה במחובר לקרקע, Im
ken matzinu Terumah be-mechubar le-karka, then you would have the phenomenon of
תרומה Terumah on something that is attached to the ground.
דמחובר לקרקע. De-mechubar le-karka. But we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, לא
מצינו תרומה במחובר לקרקע, Lo matzinu Terumah be-mechubar le-karka, we've never found
תרומה Terumah in something attached to the ground. So Abaye says back,
אמר להו, Amar lehu, no. כי תניא ההיא לענין חיובי מיתה וחומש.
Ki tanya ha-hi le-inyan chiyuvey mitah ve-chomesh. When it says there's no
תרומה Terumah by something attached to the ground, it doesn't mean there's
no תרומה. Terumah. It could be תרומה Terumah when it's attached to
the ground if you buy my scenario, if you buy my case
that it became טבל Tevel and you replanted, maybe in theory it
could be תרומה. Terumah. So what does it mean there's no תרומה?
Terumah? It means you can't be חייב chayav on it for eating
it while it's growing from the ground. Why not? Okay, מיתה וחומש
mitah ve-chomesh is if a non-כהן Kohen eats תרומה, Terumah, he's חייב
מיתה, chayav mitah, מיתה בידי שמים במזיד, mitah biydey Shamayim be-mazid, not
מיתת בית דין. mitat Beis Din. If he does it בשוגג be-shogeg
or whatever, he pays it back and adds a חומש, chomesh, a
fifth. So he says there could be no חיוב, chiyuv, even though
it could be תרומה, Terumah, you won't have a חיוב chiyuv if
you eat it while it's growing. That's what we mean no תרומה
Terumah while it's growing. Why would there not be a חיוב? chiyuv?
So he's going to tell you, דאי תלש ואכל, De-ei talash ve-achal,
because how did you eat it? If you picked it off, you
plucked it and ate it, then תלוש הוא, talush hu, then it's
not מחובר, mechubar, it's תלוש, talush, so you don't have the scenario
of eating it as when it's growing. ואי גחין ואכל, Ve-ei gachin
ve-achal, if you sort of swallowed and ate it, meaning you sort
of ate it straight from the stalk, you didn't pluck it and
eat it, you held the stalk into your mouth and you ate
it from the stalk. So there if that's true, בטלה דעתו אצל
כל אדם, batlah da'ato etzel kol adam, then you're just crazy, and
what you do has no significance and we can't consider it an
act of eating. Okay, so this is quite fascinating for a number
of reasons. Number one is that, and this assumes by the way
that the חיוב chiyuv of תרומה, Terumah, whether it's מיתה בידי שמים
במזיד mitah biydey Shamayim be-mazid or to pay back with a חומש,
chomesh, is only an act of eating. Although the idea of paying
back, you might think it's enough that you stole it, the תורה
Torah and the גמרא Gemara is very clear that no, the idea
to add a חומש chomesh is only when you misappropriate it through
eating do you add a חומש. chomesh. So what this is not
called an act of eating. So on the one hand this is
a חידוש chiddush because normally when we say it's not an act
of eating, we mean that there's something that really changes the character
of it, like the food itself normal people don't eat this, it's
not normally fit for eating, it's disgusting or something, or you stuffed
yourself with it so it was like overeating, there was something about
the sort of actual, experience that would make it not normal eating.
Here it's more like okay, you ate it off the ground, but
we're not saying that the grains that you put in your mouth
weren't fit for eating, we're just saying it's a bizarre way to
do it, to chew it off of the stalk. If I stood
on my head and chewed it, no normal person stands on their
head and chews grain, but we would still say it's an act
of אכילה, achilah, that doesn't redefine the act. So it is a
little bit interesting that now it's not the same here, here the
actual food is still connected, but that we say that's enough to
redefine the act and say it's not an act of eating because
that's not how normal people eat. That's one thing. The other thing
is, okay, so it says that we have a משנה Mishnah that
says there's no תרומה במחובר. Terumah be-mechubar. So take a look at
the side here in the מסורת הש"ס Masoret ha-Shas on the right-hand
side where right where the... right where the גמרא Gemara said that
in the brackets. So look what he says: לקוצר דעתי Likotzer Da'ati
because of my limited knowledge, לא ידעתי לציין מקומו, lo yadati letzayen
mekomo, I can't tell you where this משנה mishna is במשנה או
בברייתא שאין מפורש דבר זה. bemishna o bevraita she-ein meforash davar zeh.
I don't have any משנה mishna or ברייתא braita to refer you
to. You see that in the very right-hand column after the רש"י,
Rashi, to the right of רש"י, Rashi, right in the bracket? Right
he says, okay, the גמרא Gemara says a משנה mishna says that
you never have תרומה במחובר. truma be-mechubar. He says I don't know
of any משנה mishna or any ברייתא braita that makes this statement.
So that's a and you know he's being a little humble לקוצר
דעתי. Likotzer Da'ati. This is the person of course that cross-referenced the
entire גמרא. Gemara. So what it really means is that there isn't
a משנה mishna or ברייתא braita that says it. Now maybe it's
possible to reread the גמרא Gemara as opposed to we taught לא
מצינו תרומה במחובר lo matzinu truma be-mechubar to say you know we
never taught that there was תרומה במחובר. truma be-mechubar. You know there's
a difference between teaching that it isn't as opposed to never teaching
that it is. But maybe that's a slightly different way of reading
the גמרא. Gemara. We never find the phenomenon of תרומה במחובר truma
be-mechubar and it's crazy for you אביי Abaye to be inventing it.
But it doesn't sound that way. It sounds like the משנה mishna
believes that there's some tannaitic source that says it that it has
to explain. And אביי Abaye is now explaining by saying yes it
would be תרומה truma maybe in theory, but you won't be חייב
chayav for eating it. Okay, so now because it's not דרכו. darko.
And now the גמרא Gemara continues with that.
ומאי שנא מדכתבי אפנקסא דאילפא? U-mai shna mi-dekatvei a-pinkusa de-Ilfa? So fascinating
again, you know, these types of references. How is what you're saying
different than what is written on the notebook of אילפא? Ilfa? אילפא
Ilfa's notebook, go figure that. Here's what's written there: ביצי נבלת עוף
טהור. beitzai nivlas of tahora. Eggs of a נבלת עוף טהור, nivlas
of tahora, a kosher bird that was not slaughtered correctly. You will
remember that a נבלת עוף טהור, nivlas of tahora, a kosher bird
not slaughtered correctly, of a kosher species has the status that when
you swallow it it causes טומאה tuma through the act of eating
and through the act of swallowing. So again what is important is
to define what you're doing as an act of eating. If you
touch it it doesn't cause טומאה, tuma, if you eat it and
swallow it in a way that's defined as an act of eating
it does. So that's what's important. And now here's what is written
there: if you have this egg, מקצתן בחוץ ומקצתן בפנים. miktzasam bachutz
u-miktzasam bifnim. As the animal died, its egg was half inside its
body and half out. It was half in the process of laying
an egg and half was inside, half was out. So what happened?
מבפנים מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. mibifnim metamei begadim beveise hablia. The part
of the egg that's inside the bird is considered still part of
the bird and considered like meat and therefore if you swallow it
it will make you טמא. tamei. Again מטמא בגדים metamei begadim means
you and the clothes you're wearing. מביחוץ mibachutz the part of the
egg that's outside אין מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה ein metamei begadim beveise
hablia is not considered part of the bird and therefore if you
swallow it does not make you טמא. tamei. So and the גמרא
Gemara understands for some bizarre reason that what you're talking about here
is not just where the egg was when the bird died, but
actually where it is when you're eating it. So if you consume
the egg while it's inside the bird, then it's considered like meat.
If you removed the egg and ate it, then it's not considered
like meat. So גמרא Gemara says well why is it a problem?
If you ate it while it's inside the bird, that's not the
normal way people eat and shouldn't that be considered non-act of eating?
If you know if you can say eating from something growing is
not an act of eating.
So גמרא Gemara says how could you even divide half you ate
here the egg is all one? I would.
Right. So me I don't know yeah that's a good question how
would you...
you can't take part of it from the out.
You know what it's a great question I really don't know. Unless
what he's saying is that you're not חייב chayav just by eating
the egg, even if you ate the whole egg, a whole egg
is not a שיעור, shiur, right? And you need to eat more.
You're right. I mean you'd have to say that you ate the
whole egg but you can only you're only considered to have eaten
for טומאה tuma purposes that percentage we only pay attention to the
percentage that was on the inside. But you're right it's hard to
imagine separate. Right. So you're right you have to assume that you
ate the whole thing but we're only paying attention to for טומאה
tuma purposes to the half of it. Right. So now the גמרא
Gemara says but why why is that an act of eating? Who
eats an egg while it's still in the womb of a chicken?
Is it considered a womb by the way for fowl? Wherever they
lay the eggs from. Probably the egg factory. Anyway whatever it is.
It's a delicacy.
Really?
From מעשה שבת Maaseh Shabbos or Mensach they find chickens with eggs
in them.
Yeah I remember. But they wouldn't eat unfertilized egg raw. They wouldn't
eat it raw.
Right they'd take it out and cook it. Right. Right.
They used to give them to me I remember. All yellow though.
Yeah. Not in a shell.
Right right right.
They would be in the chicken they would find it.
Interesting. Interesting. Okay. So all right so now okay so the גמרא
Gemara says so here is the difference now. תלוש, tlush, if the
whole thing is not attached, it's a chicken, it's an egg in
a chicken. עביד אינש דאכלי הכי. avid inish d'achli hachi. Then people
can eat things that are unattached in weird ways. So they'll eat
it while it's inside the chicken. But מחובר לא עביד אינש דאכלי
mechubar lav avid inish d'achli but while it's attached nobody eats stuff
that's still attached. Now again I don't think I would not frame
it as that what percentage of people eat this way versus what
percentage eat that way. I think the question of it's not normal
is always a question of okay but is it relevant to defining...
The act of eating. Like I said, if you're standing on your
head, it's also not normal, but we don't say what you did
wasn't the act of eating. So maybe what it's saying is if
the object is not attached, then as far as the object is
concerned, it's the normal state that objects are eaten. And therefore even
if you eat it in a weird way while having an enema,
okay, but you ate a normal object which is fit to be
eaten and I don't care if you were doing weird things while
you were eating it, right? But if it's still attached, that really
redefines the object and redefines the act of eating. And therefore that's
where that we could say is not considered an act of eating.
That's how I would prefer to read the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara just ends this point, thankfully, because I think we're
all ready to get onto a new topic. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אמר רב תביומי בר קיסנא אמר שמואל. Amar
Rav Tiviumi bar Kisna Amar Shmuel. רב תביומי בר קיסנא Rav Tiviumi
bar Kisna says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הזורע כלאים בעציץ
שאינו נקוב אסור. Hazore'a Kilayim be'atzitz she'eino nakuv assur. You planted כלאים
Kilayim in a עציץ atzitz without a hole, a flowerpot without a
hole, it's forbidden. Now if that's not considered normal growing and so
on, why exactly should it be forbidden? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
בשלמא אי אשמעינן לוקה מכת מרדות מדרבנן שפיר. Bishlama i ashmi'inan loke
makkas mardus miderabbanan shapir. If you were telling us not just it
was forbidden, but that we would treat that as a because a
flowerpot without a hole is not biblical status but at least it
has a rabbinic status of being considered like ground. So אביי Abaye
says, what's the חידוש chidush of what you're saying? We already know
that these flowerpots without holes are rabbinically considered like ground. So if
you were to have made a really strong statement, we're going to
give you lashes, rabbinic lashes, שפיר, shapir, then you would have told
me a big high point that even though it's just rabbinic, at
least we're going to really punish you and give you rabbinic lashes
if you eat it. אלא אי אסור, Ella i assur, if all
you're telling me is that it's forbidden, מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma
lan? What are you telling me? דמדרבנן הויא זריעה? De'miderabbanan havya zeri'a?
That rabbinically it's considered planting? תנינא, Tenina, that's a principle we know,
that an עציץ atzitz without a hole is at least rabbinically considered
planting. How do you know that? Because we taught, התורם משאינו נקוב
על הנקוב, Hatorem mishe'eino nakuv al hanakuv, if you take תרומה terumah
from stuff that grew from a flowerpot without a hole on a
flowerpot that has a hole, so one is obligated and the other
is not and you try to take תרומה terumah from one on
the other,
תרומה ויחזור ויתרום. terumah ve'yachzor ve'yitrom. So you have to take תרומה
terumah again, because here's my stuff from my flowerpot that's without a
hole, here's with, I took the תרומה terumah from here to apply
to all of the grain, and this grain here that grew from
the stuff with a hole did not have a legitimate תרומה terumah
taken from it, so I have to take תרומה terumah again on
this grain because it was really חייב chayav and it didn't have
תרומה. terumah. That's not a חידוש. chidush. The חידוש chidush is it
said תרומה ויחזור ויתרום. terumah ve'yachzor ve'yitrom. יחזור ויתרום Yachzor ve'yitrom I
know, I have to take תרומה terumah again. But this stuff that
I took, at least does still have a status of תרומה. terumah.
Why? That would only be because the stuff that grew in the
unholed flowerpot at least is rabbinically obligated. If it wasn't even rabbinically
obligated, what I did was zero. But because it's rabbinically obligated, then
it does have a status of תרומה, terumah, but not enough because
it's only rabbinic to exempt this stuff which grew from the stuff
with a hole. So that principle that it has a rabbinic status
we know, what are you telling me? You're telling me something that
I already know. And with that we end that discussion, okay, very
intensive introduction into זרעים zera'im about תרומות ומעשרות terumot uma'asrot and stuff
that grew this way versus that way. Thankfully now we're still going
to be in some agricultural considerations but stuff that will be much
more relevant and much more familiar. So let's take a look now
at the next משנה. mishnah. החיטין והשעורין, Hachittin vehase'orin,
okay, so wheat and barley, that I know. Now here is the
other three grains, okay? והכוסמין והשיבולת שועל והשיפון. Vehakusmin vehashibolet shu'al vehashiffon.
So I made for you some nice handout
here, thanks for Hebrew Wikipedia, Hebrew Wikipedia is the new source on
הלכה Halacha anyway. Okay, so what are these things? So you take
a look here on the picture, wheat and barley, there are your
pictures for them. Okay, then כוסמין Kusmin is normally considered to be
spelt, שיבולת שועל shibolet shu'al is oats, and שיפון shiffon is normally
considered to be rye. Okay, I'll talk in a minute about whether
these are accurate identification, but normally for as somebody these are the
five Halachic grains: wheat, barley, spelt, oats and rye. And so we
will talk about these identifications in a minute. Okay, let's take a
look. הרי אלו חייבין בחלה. Harei elu chayavin bachallah. So it's exactly
this point, these are the Halachic grains and therefore what you make
out of them can become חמץ, chametz, can be used for מצה,
matzah, defines bread, any type of like baked product or you know
ideas of חמץ, chametz, מצה, matzah, bread, whatever is limited to these
five grains. So the משנה mishnah teaches: A, if you make חלה
challah out of it, it's obligated in חלה. challah. ומצטרפין זה עם
זה. Umistarfim ze im ze. And even if your חלה challah was
made not out of just wheat flour but a mix of wheat
and barley and spelt flour, you mixed it all together, so it
still they all combine to a שיעור shi'ur of חלה. challah. You
don't need a full amount from wheat, a full amount from barley,
you have a mixed flour and you make חלה challah out of
it, it's all considered a שיעור shi'ur to חייב chayav in חלה.
challah. ואסורין בחדש מלפני הפסח. Ve'asurin bechadash milifnei hapessach. That's of course
why we're teaching it here, that all of these grains are forbidden
to be eaten before the עומר Omer is brought. Meaning, although the
עומר omer is barley, it's not just that barley is forbidden, all
grains are forbidden. But only grains, right? Rice is not forbidden, right?
Fruit are not forbidden, so the grains are forbidden. So all of
these grains are forbidden before you before you bring before פסח, Pesach,
before the עומר. omer. ומיקצר מלפני העומר, Umiktzar milifnei ha'omer, and also
remember that the עומר omer is not just prohibited it's prohibited to
eat the new grains, but it's prohibited to cut, to harvest the
new grains until the עומר omer is harvested. So all of these
grains, you can pick your fruit, you can pick
your rice, but you cannot cut, you cannot harvest any of the
grains until the עומר omer is cut. And when does what does
the עומר omer work to make how does the עומר omer make
them permissible? השרישו קודם לעומר העומר מתירן. Hishrishu kodem la'omer ha'omer matiran.
If they've taken root by the time the עומר omer is brought,
then the עומר omer makes them permissible, and even if they continue
to grow, they have now been made permissible by the עומר. omer.
ואם לאו, Ve’im lav, and if they have not yet taken root,
even if they were planted, אסורין עד שיבא העומר הבא. Asurin ad
sheyavo ha'omer haba. Then they this עומר omer does not relate to
them, they only next year's עומר omer relates to them. So the
question about when does the עומר, omer, to which grain does it
apply? It's any grain that has taken root by the time the
עומר omer was brought, which is our problem by winter wheat, because
winter wheat is planted after the עומר omer and harvested after the
עומר, omer, and it's forbidden until the next עומר omer is brought.
Now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara after the identification
of these things.
So I want to ask something first. If you have a wheat
field, yes, how can you possibly tell
when it took root?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so I think you asked that the
other time, the גמרא Gemara says that the idea of taking root
is not something you look at the plant, the idea of taking
root is a certain amount of time from the time it was
planted, either two weeks or a month. There's a debate in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but or some say I think even other amounts
as well. But it's an amount of time
from No, no, I don't understand because it's going to keep growing.
Right.
But if you have to determine, had it taken root so that
the עומר omer works for it, the question is, well, when did
you plant it? If you planted it a week ago or two
weeks ago or a month ago, we'll assume it took root. If
you planted it three days ago?
You don't have to go out and say this
No, no, no, and you you count from the time it was
planted, and there's a debate, normally we assume two weeks, there's an
opinion of one month. But basically the way to reframe it is,
if it was planted two weeks before the עומר, omer, then you're
fine. Okay. That's the translation of having taken root. It's not physically
No I mean it is, but we do it based on quantifying
it and not based on looking at each case. Okay, but based
on quantifying and determining translating it into a period of time. For
exactly your concern, how else are you going to figure out?
We've had a case with the סופתא sufta that started and then
you and then you
replanted.
Yeah, but that was something
separating the תף taf from the bottom.
That's when you actually go ahead and do something different with it.
But to determine has it taken root or not, there you use
based on a period of time. So now the גמרא Gemara is
going to try to identify these. So תנא, Tana, we תנא tana
a ברייתא: braita: כוסמין, Kusmin, what is כוסמין? kusmin? מין חטין. Min
chitin. It's a type of wheat. שיבולת שועל ושיפון, Shibolet shual veshifon,
מין שעורין. min seorin. And שיבולת שועל shibolet shual and שיפון shifon
are a type of barley. Now the relevance to that is because
there's a משנה mishnah in חלה Challah that says, although our משנה
mishnah says that you can use all of these types of things
to make חלה, challah, the משנה mishnah in חלה Challah says it's
not true. You actually only if you use similar grains can they
combine to a שיעור shiur of חלה. challah. So only if you
combine כוסמין kusmin and wheat does that combine to a שיעור shiur
of חלה. challah. Not if you try to combine wheat and barley.
Those types of flour would not be considered one שיעור shiur of
חלה. challah. Or if you combine שיבולת שועל shibolet shual and שיפון
shifon and barley, that makes one type they can combine to a
שיעור shiur of חלה, challah, but not if you crossover. Okay, so
that's why it's important to categorize whether you put this into the
wheat category or the barley category, and actually it sounds actually more
than that, more that
that כוסמין kusmin really is double categorized, כוסמין kusmin is both a
type of wheat and a type of barley. Anyway, but it matters
because when you have a mixture of flours, only certain things that
are considered similar of a similar genre are considered one amount, one
שיעור, shiur, and that you can, you know, say that even though
I don't have a שיעור shiur of wheat here, I have a
total שיעור shiur combined I have a שיעור shiur and therefore it's
חייב chayav in חלה. challah. Okay, so the relevance of this is
to combine for a שיעור shiur and that's why we have to
know which category to put it in.
Now, what are the what are they? כוסמין, Kusmin, what is this
כוסמין? kusmin?
גולבא. Gulba. Wow, that explains it. So, if you look at רש״י,
Rashi, רש״י Rashi says אספילטא, Aspilta, which is
spelt. Very good. Okay. שיפון, Shifon, what's שיפון? shifon? דישרא. Dishra. That
was also helpful. So you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
סיגלא, Sigla, which וייסיך נישט, veise ich nisht, but it's normally identified
with rye. Okay, and that really does not seem to be too
much of a debate about what this דישרא dishra is. Now, שיבולת
שועל, Shibolet shual, what's שיבולת שועל? shibolet shual? So it translates it
just literally, שיבולתא דתעלא. shiboleta detala. So שיבולת, shibolet, which means— means
a stalk, so it says that’s שבולת, shibolet, same word. And תעלא
taala is a fox, שועל. shual. So it’s basically just translates, what’s
שבולת שועל? shibolet shual? It’s the stalk of a fox. Okay, anyway,
what is that? So you look at רש״י, Rashi, so רש״י Rashi
says שיבולי תעלא, shibulei taala, אבינא. avina. Now אבינא avina actually is
the scientific term for oats. So based on these רש״יs, Rashis, the
assumption is that as you said that it is oat, spelt and
rye. And especially those with the English translations that Soncino used and
therefore everybody had a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai that these
other three מינים minim are oat, spelt and rye. However, Professor Yehuda
Feliks, who wrote החי והצומח במשנה HaChai VeHaTzomeach BaMishnah and החי והצומח
במקרא, HaChai VeHaTzomeach BaMikra, he really knew flora and fauna and identifying
it in תנ״ך Tanakh and identifying it in גמרא Gemara and the
משנה. Mishnah. I was actually just looking for his book החי והצומח.
HaChai VeHaTzomeach. Anyway.
You do? We should have it somewhere in the בית מדרש. Beit
Midrash. He in particular called question to the identification of שבולת שועל
shibolet shual with oats. If you take a look, this is taken
here from again the Wikipedia, Hebrew Wikipedia, but it’s a great little
story. It says like this in the second paragraph: says Professor Yehuda
Feliks זיהה zihei identified שבולת שועל shibolet shual עם זן של השעורה
im zan shel haseora with a type of the גמרא Gemara says
that it’s a type of a barley. So this whatever this type
a particular species of barley which fits the גמרא. Gemara. וטען veta'an
and he claimed שלא ייתכן ששבולת שועל הוא סוג הדגן הקרוי בשם
זה כיום אבינא. shelo yitachen sheshibolet shual hu sug hadagan hakaru b'shem
zeh kayom avina. It is impossible against רש״י Rashi that שבולת שועל
shibolet shual means what we call שבולת שועל shibolet shual which is
אבינא avina which is oats. Why is that
a problem? מכיוון שבדגן זה mikeivan shebadagan zeh in oats אין גלוטן
ein gluten והוא לא היה מוכשר לחמץ בימי המשנה והתלמוד. vehu lo
hayah muchshar lechametz bimei HaMishnah VeHaTalmud. Two things. Number one is it
wouldn’t have been considered a grain. One of the primary things about
grain is that it can ferment and become חמץ. chametz. And he
says oats don’t have gluten and that he understood was primary in
חז״ל Chazal being prepared to consider grain. And number two, it was
not known in the times of the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא
Gemara where חז״ל Chazal lived. So it could not have been oats.
פרופסור פליקס סיפר Professor Feliks siper he says שבעקבות זיהויו shebe'ikvot zihuyu
based on his identification,
how he identified what שבולת שועל shibolet shual is, הרב שלמה זלמן
אוירבך HaRav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach היה מברך ברכת שהכל על ארוחת הבוקר
שלו שהכילה דייסת שבולת שועל במקום המזונות. hayah mevarech birkat shehakol al
aruchat haboker shelo shehechila daisat shibolet shual bimkom hamezonot.
So based on what he identified, הרב שלמה זלמן אוירבך HaRav Shlomo
Zalman Auerbach who was the great פוסק posek of that generation, when
he had oatmeal for breakfast he would say שהכל shehakol not מזונות
mezonot because oats is not one of the חמשת המינים. Chameshet HaMinim.
עד שהרב יוסף שלום אלישיב ad sheHaRav Yosef Shalom Elyashiv גער בו
ga'ar bo so הרב אלישיב Rav Elyashiv found out about this and
yelled at הרב שלמה זלמן HaRav Shlomo Zalman בטענה beta'ana שאי אפשר
לשנות מנהג ישראל של מאות שנים, she'ee efshar leshanot minhag Yisrael shel
meot shanim,
you can’t change our practice for hundreds of years to make a
בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonot on oatmeal, right? מהראשונים mehaRishonim based
on the ראשונים Rishonim probably referring to our רש״י Rashi who says
אבינא avina בגלל חוקר אחד biglal choker echad
just because of one scientist like the Professor Feliks. So it actually
is an interesting הלכה halacha question and people have written about this.
It is true רש״י Rashi says אבינא avina but look, Rabbi Love
has something he wants to contribute. Anyway, but people have really written
about this, that it is very hard to assume, Professor Feliks, based
on what חז״ל Chazal knew and on the qualities of it, that
they really were referring to oats, but we now have it like
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai that oats is one of the
חמשת המינים Chameshet HaMinim even though in practice it really is very
questionable. Rabbi Love, you wanted to move to רש״י?
Rashi? I mean, practically all the ראשונים Rishonim identified
it with oats.
All the ראשונים Rishonim who did translate it, translated אבינא. avina.
אבינא. avina. Okay.
So the שאלה shailah is only indeed whether that’s what the משנה
Mishnah meant, but I don’t think that makes a difference.
Because in the end it’s what the ראשונים Rishonim
say and all the ראשונים Rishonim פוסקים paskening that oats is a...
Right. So if the ראשונים Rishonim say it, that’s again a fascinating
little story about how
for the people who
are
celiac
who are gluten-free, to have a type of a
מצה matzah to have a type of a grain that doesn’t have
gluten. So that’s why oats is very important as well. Very interesting.
Right, and what Rabbi Love
says, which is lower in gluten than wheat, it still has wheat
and still has gluten as opposed to oats.
As opposed to oats.
So what Rabbi Love says and what’s really being said here is
actually a quite fascinating point about the nature of תורה שבעל פה
Torah SheBa'al Peh which is that it’s not about what sort of
it was originally meant by the sources, it’s about what sort of
gets to become the canonized interpretation. So all the ראשונים Rishonim are
saying it, that becomes the canonized interpretation, that becomes הלכה halacha whether
it really is what the גמרא Gemara meant as well or not.
But it is fascinating that actually I hadn’t thought about that but
it creates this benefit for people that can’t manage gluten that you
do have a grain. that is a non-gluten grain. There is a
similar question about whether spelt, but it's not as relevant, is this
כוסמין kusmin or not. Again, some say that it was actually something
called emmer wheat or farro. Does that mean anything to anybody? But
anyway, that's again what Professor Felix said was that it's not really
spelt, but again we sort of believe that it is spelt. And
I should also mention that he has, besides the sort of more
popular book חי וצומח, Chai VeTzomeach, has a couple of more heavyweight
academic books, and this one is called כלאי זרעים והרכבה, Kilay Zeraim
VeHarkava,
okay, which is, you know, crossing of seeds. And it's basically a
commentary on the משניות כלאיים, Mishnayot Kilayim, but with his, you know,
an academic commentary on the משניות כלאיים. Mishnayot Kilayim. And the first
משנה Mishnah of כלאיים Kilayim says, this is his book, the first
משנה Mishnah of כלאיים Kilayim says, החטים והזונין אין כלאים זה בזה
השעורים ושיבולת שועל הכוסמין והשיפון הפול והספיר. HaChitim ve'hazunin ein kilayim zeh
bezeh ha'seorim ve'shibolet shual ha'kusmin ve'hashippon ha'pol ve'hasappir. Anyway,
mentions in terms of כלאיים Kilayim these various species, and he goes
and he identifies them. And he basically says, and here is a
picture.
So that's wheat.
This is... where's the other
picture? Okay, that's barley, שיבולת שועל, shibolet shual, which he identified Hordeum
distinctum.
Okay, whatever, so which anyway is not oats but is, you know,
whatever he says it was,
something else. And here's the avena, which here is the oat. And
anyway he has this other picture. So here he does a whole
thing of identifying what those species are. I was not able to
find the חי וצומח Chai VeTzomeach book. Anyway, so there you go,
those are the five species of grain. Now let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with it. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says, הני אין,
hani in, these yes, these are considered
grains, אורז ודוחן לא, orez vedochan lo,
rice and... I don't know what's דוחן. dochan. Rabbi Love, what's דוחן?
dochan?
Millet. Okay, thank you. Rice and millet not. So those are not
grains. מנני מילי, minani milei, where do we know this from? אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, אתיא לחם לחם ממצה. asya lechem lechem
mimatzah. It says we make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava לחם לחם
lechem lechem from מצה. matzah. Again, this first discussion is for חלה,
challah, for the מצוה mitzvah of חלה, challah, based on the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava לחם לחם lechem lechem from מצה. matzah. כתיב הכא,
ketiv hacha,
it says here, והיה באכלכם מלחם הארץ, vehaya bachalechem milechem ha'aretz, when
you eat from the bread of the land that you have to
take חלה. challah. וכתיב התם, uchetiv hatam, and it says by מצה,
matzah, לחם עוני, lechem oni, bread of affliction. והתם גופא מנלן, vehatam
gufa minalan, and how do you know that there it refers only
to these five grains? So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, tana devei Rabbi Ishmael, וכן תנא דבי רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב, vechen tana devei Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says,
לא תאכל עליו חמץ שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות לחם עוני. lo
tochal alav chametz shivat yamim tochal alav matzot lechem oni. דברים הבאים
לידי חימוץ, devarim habaim lidei chimutz, if it's something that could ferment
and become חמץ, chametz, אדם יוצא בהן ידי חובתו בפסח, adam yotzei
bahen yedei chovato bapesach, and then it can also become
מצה. matzah. דברים שאין בהן לידי חימוץ, devarim she'ein bahen lidei chimutz,
יצאו אלו, yatzu elu, to exclude rice and millet, שאין בהן לידי
חימוץ אלא לידי סירחון. she'ein bahen lidei chimutz ela lidei sirchon. What
they do is not considered fermenting, it's considered a type of spoiling.
Now fermenting is a type of spoiling, but anyway, and therefore it's
not fermenting and it's not חמץ. chametz. And this is really the
key. חז"ל's Chazal identification of these five מינים minim are saying only
these are what we would say is cause ferments and can become
חמץ, chametz, nothing else. But yes all of these, and therefore anything
that requires מצה, matzah, חמץ, chametz, לחם, lechem, any sense of bread
or bread products or anything like that is only something from things
that ferment, and they identified these five and excluded things like rice
and millet. Now I believe, Rabbi Love here can agree or disagree,
Rabbi Love, that rice and millet actually don't have any significant scientific
characteristic different from these five species, that they have
gluten... No they don't... They don't...
Rice has no gluten...
and
millet has no...
and they don't sour, they rot.
There is a difference? I thought I heard that somebody, maybe I
misheard, okay maybe I misheard, I thought that somebody, maybe it was
like J. David Bleich or whatever, somebody sort of looked into it
and couldn't understand why חז"ל Chazal were treating it different. But you're
saying there is a difference...
They don't make flour out of it...
It does not rise...
it won't rise when wet, it will just go green or smell
but it won't...
Interesting. Okay, so there you go.
They definitely don't have gluten because I know I eat them and
I have celiac, they make it for celiacs.
Okay, very good. So that's what it's saying. So these do not
ferment, they rot, and apparently they don't have gluten. I think that's
the key and that's also why Professor Felix was very bothered with
oats, because he felt that the whole difference was the issue of
gluten. Anyway, and therefore these are not grains that become bread or
חמץ. chametz. Now we go on with this, ומצטרפים זה עם זה,
umitzatrfim zeh im zeh, they can combine with one another, different types
of flour, to be an amount to being חלה. challah. תנו, tanu,
so we've learned in a ברייתא, Baraisa, התרואה והקמחים והבציקות, hatrua vehakamachim
vehabatzekot,
so whether you have the whole grain itself or flour or doughs...
starting מצטרפים
זה עם זה, mitztarfim zeh im zeh, they would combine in order
for various הלכות. halachot. Now, גמרא Gemara asks, למאי, lemai, what הלכה?
halacha? It can't be חלה, challah, because you only take חלה challah
from dough. So if you're talking about the grain itself combining or
the flour, you're not talking about חלה. challah. So for what הלכה
halacha do we say that these various products combine? So it says
למאי הלכתא, lemai hilchata, for what הלכה? halacha? אמר רב כהנא, Amar
Rav Kahana, לעניין חדש, le’inyan chadash, for the other part of our
משנה mishna always when we're talking about this, that if you ate
a כזית kezayit of new grain from a mixture of grains and
flours and dough of all these different products, you'd be חייב chayav
for eating a כזית kezayit of חדש chadash and you'd get lashes.
Okay, so to make you transgress for חדש, chadash, all these different
grains and all these different states combine. That's what he says. רב
יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, לעניין חמץ בפסח, le'inyan chametz b’Pesach, another
prohibition. Let's say it all fermented. So in order to be חייב
chayav for eating a כזית kezayit of חמץ, chametz, whether it's in
different states and whether it's different grains, they would combine. And רש"י
Rashi points out you can get חמץ chametz even from a whole
grain. It doesn't have to be flour. If you add water to
the grain and the grain cracks, it can ferment. So therefore these
various grains and flours, whatever state they're in, and even if they're
different genres, combine to make a כזית kezayit to transgress either for
חדש chadash or for חמץ. chametz. Okay, those are good answers. So
רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, לעניין מעשר שני, le’inyan ma’aser sheni,
for מעשר שני ma’aser sheni purposes, דאכליה חוץ לחומה, de’achlei chutz lachomah,
if you ate this outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, because you have to
eat מעשר שני ma’aser sheni in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, לקי, loki, you get
lashes. That is not a great answer because מעשר שני ma’aser sheni
has nothing to do with it being a grain. מעשר שני ma’aser
sheni applies to all, you know, produce. So why would I talk
about different grains combining? It would suggest that different grains and fruit
don't combine. But מעשר שני ma’aser sheni has nothing to do with
the status of being a grain, so that is a strange idea.
Okay, רבא אמר, Rava amar, לעניין טומאת אוכלין, le’inyan tumat ochlin, that
they all combine in order to be considered a כביצה kebeitzah of
food in order to receive and transmit טומאה. tumah. Only things that
are considered food receive and transmit טומאה. tumah. You need a certain
amount, a כביצה, kebeitzah, and therefore that's what it is, that even
if they're in different states and even if they're different grains, wheat
and spelt and barley, different states and different grains, they combine for
a כזית kezayit of
טומאה. tumah. והא קמשמע לן, Veha kamashma lan, סיכייא דתבואה וקמחים, sikyaya
detvuah vekamchim, that what things become טומאה tumah for food for טומאה,
tumah, that it's only grain and flour, דומיא דבצקות, dumya debatzakos, if
they're in a similar state as dough.
Only if they're in a similar state as dough, only then are
they considered food. What does that mean?
והא קמשמע לן, Veha kamashma lan, I'm sorry, מה התם אוכלא בעיניה,
mah hatam ochla be’einiah, the same way dough is real food, אף
הכא נמי אוכלא בעיניה, af hacha nami ochla be’einiah, here too real
food. והא דתנן, Veha detnan, what does that mean? What are you
excluding? והא תניא, Veha tanya, like we teach in a ברייתא, braita,
חיטה, chitah, if you have wheat, בין קלופה בין שאינה קלופה, bein
klufah bein she'einah klufah, מצטרפת, mitztarefet, whether it is shelled or not
shelled, whether the shell's on it or not, if you have a
pile of wheat, it all combines to the size of a כביצה,
kebeitzah, of an egg, to be considered food and to become טמא.
tamei. The shell there is not a problem. Why? Because presumably the
shell is edible. It's what the גמרא Gemara said is אוכלא בעיניה.
ochla be’einiah. And since it's edible, it's also considered to be food.
שעורה, se’orah, however, when it comes to barley, only קלופה מצטרפת, klufah
mitztarefet, only shelled
barley combines to become an amount for
food for טומאה. tumah. שאינה קלופה אין מצטרפת, she'einah klufah ein mitztarefet,
if it's not shelled, it does not combine, because the shell is
inedible and is not considered food. So that's what he's saying is
what it's telling you, all these things, grains and flours and dough
combine, but it has to be like dough. It has to be
edible. So if what you're using is the shells of barley, that
would not combine. If the barley still has the shells on, it's
not edible. רש"י Rashi goes so far to say that even the
amount that's inside the shells doesn't combine because the shell creates a
חציצה הפסק chatzitzah hefsek between one thing of food and another thing
of food. So it's not like all the food is touching because
the shells get in the way. The hulls, thank you. Right, I
know shells are like peanuts. Hull is the better term. Thank you.
The hulls. The hulls get in the way. So that's what it's
telling you, the hulls of barley do not combine for food.
איני? Ini? The גמרא Gemara says, is that true? והתנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, Vehatana devei Rabbi Yishmael, we learn in the house of רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, על כל זרע זרוע אשר יזרע, al kol zera
zerua asher yizarei, it says if water falls on any seed that
is planted, that it's considered, that it's susceptible to טומאה. tumah. And
we say what does it mean a seed that is planted, that
can be planted? כדרך שבני אדם מוציאים לזריעה, kederech shebnei adam motzi'im
lizriah, in a state where people take the seed out to be
planted. חיטה בקליפתה ושעורה בקליפתה, chitah beklipatah us’orah beklipatah, that you would
take out the wheat with its hull and the barley with its
hull and you plant these things with their hull. So his דרשה
drasha is the פסוק pasuk says as it is planted, which means
even with its hull it's considered food and can become
טמא. tamei. ועדשים בקליפתן, ve’adashim beklipatan, and the legumes in their hulls,
in their shells. So you see it can become טמא tamei even
with the shell. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. הא בלחות הא ביבשות. ha belachot ha beyaveshot. If
it's moist, then the shells are edible and therefore it is considered
food and therefore it can become טמא tamei with the shell. However...
If it's dry, the shells are inedible, the hulls are inedible, then
that prevents it from combining to be considered food, and as רש״י
Rashi says, even the food part doesn't combine because the hull gets
in the way. Okay, so that is the idea of מצטרפין, mitstarfin,
whatever different types of grain, different types of state, they still combine
for various הלכות, halakhot, for חמץ chametz and for חדש chadash and
so on. Let's just read a little bit more here. ואסור בחדש
מלפני הפסח, ve'asur bechadash milifnei hapessach, and you can't eat its new
grain, so all of these five grains even if it's not just
barley cannot be eaten before פסח. Pesach. So מנא הני מילי, minayin
mili, where do you know this from, that the prohibition applies to
all grains, not just barley? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, אתיא
לחם לחם ממצה, ataya lechem lechem mimatzah, because it says don't eat
לחם וקלי וכרמל, lechem vekali vekarmel, don't eat bread. So since we've
already proven that bread means things that ferment and we got that
from מצה, matzah, so here it says don't eat bread, so it
means any of the grains. So not just don't eat barley, but
don't eat anything that can be used to make bread, don't eat
any of the grains and the prohibition of חדש chadash applies to
all of them. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.